<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The requests presented vnto the French King, by the generall deputies of the Reformed Churches of France Together with his Maiesties answers therevnto.</title>
            <author>Eglises réformées de France.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118734</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853941</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853941</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19344</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01192)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19344)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1065:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The requests presented vnto the French King, by the generall deputies of the Reformed Churches of France Together with his Maiesties answers therevnto.</title>
                  <author>Eglises réformées de France.</author>
                  <author>Maniald, Étienne.</author>
                  <author>Montmartin, Esaïe du mats de.</author>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Dawson] for Nathaniel Butter and William Sheffard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Montmartin Deputy Generall. Maniald Deputy Generall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reformed Church --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19344:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REQVESTS PRESENTED VNTO THE FRENCH KING, By the Generall Deputies of the Reformed Churches of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with his Maieſties Anſwers therevnto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter</hi> and <hi>William Sheffard.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19344:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19344:2"/>
            <head>To the King.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our moſt humble and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Servants and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the RELIGION, throughly informed of your Maieſties Royall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to re-eſtabliſh the ruines of your poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, haue charged the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Deputies, which it hath pleaſed your Maieſtie to grant them, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite wiſhes and acclamations to be vowed vnto the aſſured ſetling of this ſo much deſired Peace, to the end that for as much as they find themſelues pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated with ſo celeſtiall a benefit, they may ſeeke the continuance thereof, with the conſtancie of their ſubmiſſions, and by the onely recourſe, which they haue vnto your Clemencie and Iuſtice, they may giue a notable teſtimony, that they aſpire vnto
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19344:3"/>
no aſſurance or refuge more availeable againſt the violence of ſuch as trouble them, and that oppoſe the power of your Lawes, then with moſt humble requeſts and ſupplication, to invoke the firmeneſſe of your inviolable Word, and the obſervation of your ſo authenticall Briefes. For ſeing that the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages which are done them doe ſtrike directly at the reverence of your Protections, and devide that which the Peace &amp; their obedience ought to ioyne vnder the felicitie of your Commandements, they earneſtly beſeech your Maieſtie, to weigh their moſt humble remonſtrances in that ballance of equitie, which makes your Scepter ſo iuſt and redoubtable, and that you will be pleaſed to cut off with the ſword which God hath put into your hand, the violent infringements of your gracious conceſſions, to the end that relying in a true confidence on the wiſedome and goodneſſe of your holy adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they may be alwayes retained within the fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and true obligations of your pure and entire ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <div n="1" type="request">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>VVHerfore to enioy a full effect of your juſtice, they moſt humbly beſeech your Maieſtie would be pleaſed to ſend into your Provinces, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages both of the one and the other Religion, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with that affection which is requiſite for the Peace, to the end they may the more profitably put your Edicts and Declarations in execution there, and take order in all places for the ſupplications, and neceſſities of your people of the Religion.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19344:3"/>
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>THe King hath deputed and diſpatched away Commiſſioners, as well Catholiques as of the pretended Reformed Religion into the Provinces where they are iudged neceſſary, for the execution of his Maieſties declaration of the 20. of <hi>October</hi> laſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="request">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>ANd imparting your compaſſion and clemencie to thoſe of your Townes, which haue rendered you ſuch obedience, that thereby you were pleaſed to grant vs the Peace, your Maieſtie is moſt humbly brought to ordaine, that the garriſon which for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny months hath beene with ſo much oppreſſion at <hi>Montpellier,</hi> may be withdrawne from thence, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your Royall promiſes, and in regard of the miſery and mortalitie which is in the Towne.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>AFter ſatiſfaction hath beene made to that which was ordained by the Declaration of the 20. of <hi>October</hi> laſt, his Maieſtie will take order for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the preſent Article.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="request">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>ANd that conformably to the particular Briefe, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it hath pleaſed your Maieſty to accord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nothing may be innovated in your ſaid towne of <hi>Montpellier,</hi> and expreſly in that which concerneth their Conſullſhips; and that alſo the innovation made concerning the Conſullſhip, called <hi>de Mer,</hi> may be repaired, conſidering the obedience which is rendered vnto you there, in the demoliſhment of the fortifications, in which labour the inhabitants continue with great charge, care, and diligence.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19344:4"/>
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>THe Election of the Conſulls <hi>de Mer,</hi> of the ſaid Towne of <hi>Montpellier,</hi> having beene made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an Arreſt contradictorily given in the Chamber of the Edict of <hi>Caſtres,</hi> nothing can be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered or changed therein. As for the Election of the other Conſulls of the ſaid Towne, his Maieſties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is, that it ſhould be done with the ordinary formes, and according to the liberties and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="request">
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <p>YOur Subiects of the Religion alſo for to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all occaſion of diſtruſt and feare, having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſatisfaction to your Maieſties pleaſure, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the razing downe of the Forts of the Iles of <hi>Olleron</hi> and <hi>de Re;</hi> may it pleaſe your Maieſtie in like manner to ordaine, that the Fort erected before your Towne of <hi>Rochell</hi> may be demoliſhed, as it pleaſed your ſaid Maieſtie to promiſe.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>VPon hearing the report of the Commiſſioners, which his Maieſtie hath ſent to the ſaid towne of <hi>Rochell,</hi> his Maieſty will take order for that which is contained in the preſent Article.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="request">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>ANd as God is all mercy, ſo like vnto him, whoſe image you beare, may it pleaſe your Maieſtie to grant vnto a great number of perſons, of all ages, detained for being in the laſt Warre, or for Religion, in your Galleyes, with nakedneſſe, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and inſupportable vſage, their pardon and libertie; and the ſame libertie to all others that are priſoners for accuſations, depending vpon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19344:4"/>
the times and affaires of the ſaid troubles, whether they be found iudged or no; which fauor, pardon and liberty, is accorded vnto them by the 73 Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Edict which it hath pleaſed you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>His Maieſtie will deliuer the priſoners of warre, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at this preſent in the Gallies; and for thoſe which are accuſed of particular crimes, he will take order by the waies of Iuſtice.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="request">
               <head>6</head>
               <p>Your Maieſty, by your Letters of declaration of the 24 of April, 1621, hath willed that your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, which remaine in your obedience, ſhall enioy the grace and conceſſions granted vnto them, aſwell by your Maieſty, as by the late King, <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> of glorious memorie: Neuertheleſſe, the laſt yeere 1622, they haue beene wholly depriued of the money which your Maieſty was accuſtomed yeerely to cauſe to be diſtributed to them, by <hi>Monſiur du Candal</hi> the Commiſſioner for it, wherby their poore Churches are in particular ſo diſaccomodated, that they are conſtrained to haue recourſe vnto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, and beſeech you (as moſt humbly they doe) to appoint a ſtock of money vnto the ſaid <hi>du Candal</hi> for the ſaid yeere, at leaſtwiſe for the entertainment of the Paſtors of the Prouinces which remained in your obedience, and which were faine to borrow for to buy themſelues meate, and to ſupply their other neceſſities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="request">
               <head>7</head>
               <p>Likewiſe, they moſt humbly beſeech your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19344:5"/>
that according to the Grant you were pleaſed not long ſince to make vnto your ſaid Subiects, you would be pleaſed to ordaine, that the ſaid <hi>du Candal</hi> may be furniſhed with good and valuable aſſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for the entertainment and releefe of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters during the preſent yeare: and for the penſions of the parties of the <hi>petit Eſtate,</hi> which it ſhal pleaſe you to erect; as alſo for the entertainment of the places which it pleaſed you to leaue in their guard; And that all theſe aſſignations may bee paid in ſuch manner as it hath pleaſed your ſaid Maieſty, and the ſaid late King to grant vnto them by the Briefes which they haue had heretofore.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer to the 6. and 7.</head>
                  <p>The Kings affaires not permitting him to ſatisfie the ſuppliants for that, which concerneth the time paſt, his Maieſty for the time to come will cauſe good and valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſsignations to be deliuered to the ſaid <hi>du Candal</hi> for the releefe and entertainment of the ſaid Miniſters, as alſo for the payment of the penſions contained in the <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit Eſtate</hi> which he meaneth to erect. As for the Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the Briefe of the <hi>24.</hi> of October laſt ſhall be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="request">
               <head>8</head>
               <p>And foraſmuch as there reſteth great and nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſummes vnpaid of the aſſignations wherewithall the ſaid <hi>du Candal</hi> was furniſhed in the yeares 1620. and 1621, which the Receiuers and Farmers vpon whom the ſaid aſſignations were laid, keepe ſtill in their hands, they moſt humbly beſeech your Maieſty to ordaine that all delayes ſet apart, he may be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the ſaid remainders.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19344:5"/>
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The ſaid du Candal preſenting his requeſt to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, order ſhall be taken for him therein.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="request">
               <head>9</head>
               <p>The Churches of the Prouince of <hi>Gex</hi> hauing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed entertainment for their Paſtors out of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall reuennues of the ſaid Prouince, vntill the yeare 1601, and for many yeares after, vnder the late King <hi>Henry the great,</hi> and till ſuch time as it pleaſed your Maieſty by an Arreſt of your Councell of the 5 of <hi>December</hi> 1612, to take away the ſaid Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall lands, and in exchange thereof to ordaine that 3600 liuers ſhould be paid them yearly, the ſaid ſumme of 3600 liuers to bee leuyed vpon the 45000 liuers of augmentation, granted to thoſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which money was paid them by the ſaid <hi>du Candal</hi> vntill the moneth of October, 1621: May it pleaſe your Maieſtie to command they may enioy the effect of the ſaid Grant and Exchange, and to that end cauſe neceſſary aſſignations to be giuen to the ſaid <hi>du Candal,</hi> as well for payment of the arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, as of that which is to come</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The King will take order hereafter, for that which is contained in the preſent Article, according as is aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="request">
               <head>10</head>
               <p>May it pleaſe your Maieſtie alſo, to extend your liberalitie ſo farre forth as to furniſh your ſubiects of the Religion in your city of <hi>Paris</hi> with a ſtock ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for re-edifying &amp; reeſtabliſhment of their church and other buildings for the place of their exerciſe,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19344:6"/>
which were burnt, demoliſhed, and the moſt part of the materials carried away in the popular tumult that hapned in the yeere 1621, notwithſtanding that your ſaid Subiects kept themſelues within the terms of obedience, and thereby vnder your Maieſties ſafe-guard and protection.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>His Maieſty referres the re-eſtabliſhment of the ſaid Church to the care and diligence of the Suppliants.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="request">
               <head>11</head>
               <p>And after the ſame manner entreating your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the ſaid profeſſion in your Citie of <hi>Tours,</hi> may it pleaſe you Sir to furniſh them with the ſummes which your Maieſty, of your grace granted vnto them for the re-edifying of their Church; the Site and place whereof, may it pleaſe your Maieſty to continue vnto them, as that which was adiudged them by the Commiſſioners, after hearing of the whole Clergy, the Courts of Iuſtice and the Citie, and alſo was bought, built, and peaceably enioyed by them, vntill the troubles of the yeere 1621, in the poſſeſſion whereof, they were not onely maintained by the Edict of 98; but alſo by thoſe of the yeeres 1610 and 1612, and more eſpecially by your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties laſt declaration.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The Commiſsioners deputed for the Prouince of <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> ſhall take order that the Suppliants may haue a commodious place for the exerciſe of the pretended refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion. As for the re-eſtabliſhment and re-edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19344:6"/>
of their Church, his Maieſty referres the care ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto the Suppliants.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="request">
               <head>12</head>
               <p>The ſame requeſt is made vnto your Maieſty, for the re-edifying of the Church of <hi>Bourg,</hi> in the place which they of the Religion were poſſeſſed of, by the iudgement &amp; ordinance of the Commiſſioners, but now are kept from enioying it.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The Commiſsioners which are to be ſent into <hi>Breſſe,</hi> ſhall take order for that is contained in the preſent Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ſo far forth, as ſhall ſtand with reaſon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="request">
               <head>13</head>
               <p>Pleaſeth your Maieſtie to bee informed, that the inhabitants, profeſſing the reformed Religion, in your Towne of <hi>Villemur,</hi> are moleſted in the liberty of their Conſciences; depriued of all exerciſe of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie; excluded from publike office, and greatly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by the Gariſon there. They alſo of <hi>Fonte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay le Comte,</hi> are chaſed away and interdicted from Preaching and Prayer, neither can they haue their Church againe, which is euen quite ruined, nor is their Paſtor ſuffered ſo much as to enter into it, nor are they permitted to burie their dead, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe endure all exceſſe of charge and taxations, and vpon their complaints are ſent away to your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: Whereupon may it pleaſe you, Sir, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from ſuch oppreſſions, and letting them enioy the fruite of the Peace, ordaine the re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of their Religion, their Churches, their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19344:7"/>
Paſtors, the ſuretie of their Sepultures, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer elſe appertaineth vnto your Iuſtice in other their grieuances.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="request">
               <head>14</head>
               <p>May it pleaſe your Maieſty in like manner to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine the ſaid re-eſtabliſhment of the Exerciſe at <hi>Luſſon,</hi> where it is denied vnto them of the Religion, contrary to the publication of your Declaration, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they carried themſelues in all obedience, and that the ſaid Exerciſe hath beene continued there for 55 yeeres together, euen during all the time of the laſt warres, and gouernment of <hi>Monſieur Roches Baritault.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="request">
               <head>15</head>
               <p>They of the Religion alſo are diſturbed in the ſaid Exerciſe at <hi>Talmont,</hi> the Cannon hauing beene planted againſt them, vpon their aſſembly to heare a Sermon. Likewiſe at <hi>Surgers,</hi> the Lady of the place hath forbidden to Preach there, although it was permitted them all the time of theſe laſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: So in like ſort at <hi>Baignols,</hi> at <hi>S. Gilles</hi> in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc,</hi> at <hi>Figeac</hi> in <hi>Quercy,</hi> and at <hi>Vic</hi> in <hi>Armaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nac,</hi> from whence <hi>Monſieur Teſtas</hi> the Miniſter was expelled, and dares not returne thither, nor can be therewith any ſafety: wherein your Declaration being violated, may it pleaſe your Maieſty to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the re-eſtabliſhment of the ſaid Churches, and of the ſaid <hi>Teſtas;</hi> as alſo that of the Church of <hi>Quilleboeuf</hi> and the Paſtor thereof, who a long time hath ſued to be reſtored.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>To the <hi>13, 14</hi> &amp; <hi>15</hi> Articles, the Commiſsioners are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19344:7"/>
charged to ſee that the Suppliants may receiue ſatisfaction touching their demands, according to the tenor of the Edicts and the ſaid Declaration.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="request">
               <head>16</head>
               <p>And whereas the Catholiques of your Towne of <hi>Poictiers</hi> haue impoſed the ſumme of 1200 liuers vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe of the Religion, for the entertainment of a guard which they vſed in theſe troubles, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into they would not admit any of the aforeſaid Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, may it pleaſe your Maieſty to diſcharge them of it, as of an impoſition that is not reaſonable.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>16</hi> Article ſhall be communicated to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior and Sheriffs of <hi>Poictiers,</hi> that vpon hearing of them order may be taken for it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="request">
               <head>17</head>
               <p>Further they beſeech your Maieſty to ordaine, that the Edict of Exchange touching the Churches of your Soueraignty of <hi>Bearne,</hi> may in all points be effected, as it pleaſed you to accord, by the Briefe giuen at <hi>Montpellier.</hi> And that the Exerciſe of hte Religion, and the Miniſterie may bee reſtored in your Towne of <hi>Nauarrins.</hi> That in conſideration of the Ceſſion of other Churches, they of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion may be maintained in the poſſeſſion of the Churches, bells and Church-yards, which was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them by the Commiſſioners, or by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon their report. That the Colledges and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademies may be re-eſtabliſhed there, with payment of the ſtipends which were formerly allowed.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19344:8"/>
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The King will cauſe that to be carefully accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and obſerued, which was accorded to them of the pretended reformed Religion, by the Briefe of the <hi>24.</hi> of October laſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="request">
               <head>18</head>
               <p>And becauſe Iuſtice is that which moſt imports your Authority, and the conſeruation of the Peace; May it pleaſe your Maieſty to ordaine the ſpeedy re-eſtabliſhment of the Courts of Iuſtice equally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of Catholikes, and thoſe of the reformed Religion, in places and Townes where they were wont to be. And that during the time of attending the effect of the ſaid re-eſtabliſhment, the Courts of Parliament may be interdicted from taking notice and iudging of cauſes appertaining to them of the Religion: And that all appeales, either verball or written, interiected by them before Iudges, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, that are to giue Arreſts and iudgements, may haue the like effect, as if they were relieued by Royall Letters, according to the 45 Article of the Edict, and the 6 of the Conference at <hi>Nerac.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>His Maieſty intends that the Court of Iuſtice of the Edict of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> which only remaineth vn-re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, ſhall be reſtored as ſoone as may be in the Towne of <hi>Caſtres,</hi> according to the ſaid Declaration.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="request">
               <head>19</head>
               <p>By the 6 Article of the Edict, and the 2 of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and other anſwers made to the Requeſts, they of the Religion finde themſelues to be iuſtly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19344:8"/>
from contributing to the conſtructions &amp; reparations of the Church &amp; the dependances ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as a thing contrary to their conſciences. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which, the Catholike inhabitants of <hi>Arnay le Duc</hi> ſue to your Councell for leaue, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe generally on the Commonalty, as well vpon thoſe of the Religion, as vpon themſelues, the ſumm of 6000 liuers, to build a Church for the <hi>Capuchins,</hi> which would be neyther reaſonable, nor conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your Edicts: Wherefore, may it pleaſe your Maieſtie, to declare all your ſubiects of the Religion to be quit, and exempted from payments, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions of the like nature, and that the ſaid ſecond Article of the Particulars may be executed.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>It is granted.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="request">
               <head>20</head>
               <p>It is well knowne, that during theſe laſt troubles, they of the ſaid Religion haue ſuffered much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence from their contraries: As in the towne of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merantin,</hi> where the place of their Exerciſe in the ſuburbs of the ſaid towne was twice burnt. But that which is yet more ſtrange is this, that ſince the Peace which it pleaſed your Maieſtie to grant vnto your ſaid Subiects, the Church which had been built long agoe in your towne of <hi>Iergeau</hi> was quite pulled downe, and the demoliſhments carried cleane away, by meanes whereof they of the Religion are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of their Exerciſe: Wherefore they moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech your Maieſty, that in reparation of ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table an infraction of your Edicts and Declarations, you wil be pleaſed to ordaine, that the ſaid churches
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19344:9"/>
may be re-edified, and the Exerciſe re-eſtabliſhed in the ſaid townes of <hi>Iergeau</hi> and <hi>Romerantin.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The ſaid Commiſsioners deputed for thoſe places, haue in charge, to take order for that which is contained in this Article.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="request">
               <head>21</head>
               <p>Your townes of <hi>Saint Foy</hi> and <hi>Bergerac,</hi> moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech you, Sir, that you will be pleaſed out of your ſingular bountie to diſcharge them of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, which with ſo much exceſſe they haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a long time, letting your ſaid towne of <hi>Berge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rac</hi> fully enioy the benefit of your inuiolable promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by hindring ſo many innouations, and the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Cittadell there, which is now erecting no withſtanding that your Subiects of the Religion haue maintained themſelues in the firmnes of a moſt humble ſubiection and obedience towards your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, therby labouring to deſerue the effect of the ſaid Roiall promiſes, their libertie, and the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able exerciſe of their Religion.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>His Maieſty will write vnto my Lord the Duke of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpernon,</hi> Governor and Lieutenant generall in Guienne, to take order that the Inhabitants of the ſaid townes of <hi>Bergerac</hi> and <hi>Saint Foy</hi> may be releeued, and fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly entreated vpon all occaſions that ſhall preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and to ſee that the men of warre in the ſaid pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may liue in ſuch order, as they may receiue no kinde of oppreſsion from them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="request">
               <head>22</head>
               <p>And laſtly, for the eaſing of your people of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19344:9"/>
Religion, for the ſetling of them in a ſure confidence and further confirmation of the Peace, which you haue vouchfaſed to grant them: may it pleaſe your Maieſty to raze out all the market of diffidence that are yet remaining, and for that one to diſcharge the many Gariſons that ſtill continue in the lower <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc,</hi> and other Prouinces, vnder the command of ſuch as are not very well affected to your ſaid ſubiects of the religion: that ſo there may be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tardment of the effects of that obedience, which both they will and ought to render you, as well in the demoliſhments you haue ordained, as in all other things which it ſhall pleaſe you to command them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Montmartin</hi> Deputy Generall.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Maniald</hi> Deputy Generall.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The King will take order herein, as he ſhall ſee it to be beſt for his ſeruice.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed <list>
                           <item>LOVYS.</item>
                           <item>And a little lower, Philipeaux.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
